Being the country's largest government bank has
many advantages, such as a significant customer
base, trust in its name, a vast
network of branches,
and strong financial
position. Yes, I'm talking about State
Bank of India (SBI).
With a market cap of ₹7 lakh crore, SBI
is India's largest government bank, and
all its subsidiaries benefit from it. This also
benefits its associated businesses. Today, in this video,
we bring you a report card of
SBI General's health insurance
business: how is SBI General Insurance
Company's health insurance?
What are the health insurance plans it
offers its policyholders? What does SBI General's past
health claim settlement data
reveal? What is the company's track record
in claim settlement?
We'll also explore this and understand the claims process:
how can you file a cashless and reimbursement claim?
How many cashless network hospitals exist across
India? This is very important information
about this company today.  In the video, we are going to
discuss and
after thoroughly reviewing the company, what is my opinion
on the health insurance policies of this company, that is,
what
shortcomings do I see and what good things do I see,
I will also tell you that, that is,
if you have watched today's video, then you will
easily understand whether you should take SBI General's
health insurance plan or
not, so why wait, let's quickly
start this video. SBI General
Insurance Company was started in 2009
with a joint venture of State Bank of India i.e. SBI and IAG i.e. Insurance Australia Group. Later
in 2020, IAG i.e. Insurance Australia
Group made a complete exit from this joint venture
and currently, the
majority stake holder is SBI,
which has a 68% stake in this company.
Napean Opportunity LLP has a 16% stake
and Honey Witt Investments has a 10% stake.
With a market share of about 5%, SBI General
Insurance Company has become the sixth largest
private general insurance company in India.
SBI General Insurance
Company has only 146
branches across India, employing over 8,000 employees.
However,
the company's biggest distribution benefit comes
from the State Bank of India's branches, which have
over 22,500 branches across India, through which
it distributes its policies and products to every
corner of India. Therefore, the
group accidental policy you're forced to provide when opening an account with SBI is from
SBI General Insurance Company.
Let's explore the
various health
insurance plans offered by SBI General Insurance Company and the
features they offer. The
first plan is Health Edge,
a comprehensive health
insurance plan that allows you to purchase both
family floater and individual health
insurance policies. It offers a
wide range of coverage, including
unlimited restoration. There are no
standard features,
and it also offers 18 optional covers, meaning
18 add-ons.  Through which you
can completely modify your policy. The
second popular plan is their
Super Health Insurance Plan. You must have
heard the name SBI Super Health Insurance
Plan. Currently, there are a total of five variants in this plan,
as a Prime
variant has been recently launched. This is the latest
launch. Earlier, there were only
four variants in this plan. In this plan,
you get coverage from basic to higher end
in different variants like
OPD and Maternity. You will get these facilities in
different variants of Super Health Insurance.
SBI General Insurance
also has a total of four plans in the Arogya series -
Arogya Sanjivani, Arogya Supreme, Arogya Top
Up Plan and Arogya Plus Policy. Out of these, the
Arogya Plus policy has been withdrawn,
about which you must be aware. The one
which had the same premium for life time was the
SBI General Arogya Plus policy. There was
no change in the premium for life time, but now this product has been withdrawn. So,
currently
only three plans are available in the Arogya series.
Sanjeevani Arogya Supreme and Arogya
Top-Up Policy: Talking about the Super Top-Up
plan, SBI General's latest plan has been
launched, under which you
get coverage ranging from ₹ lakh to ₹ crore.
Apart from this, you
can also take personal accidental policies, in which
you can choose coverage on an individual basis or on a family floater basis.
Accidental death and disabilities can be
covered under personal accidental policies. Apart from this,
you will also get a critical illness policy from SBI General,
under which you will get coverage for serious illnesses.
However, the number of critical illnesses
covered by this plan is very less.
Only 13 critical illnesses will be covered under this plan.
You will also get a hospital cash policy in SBI General, in
which
you can avail the benefit on a per-day basis for hospitalization. That is, you will get a
daily cash benefit for the number of days of treatment in
addition to the treatment. As for
travel insurance policies, if you are
traveling abroad and
need a policy for that, then that option is also available with SBI
General.  It is available in. Now, this was about
health insurance plans, and other types
of policies, which
I saw in very limited numbers, now let's talk about this
company's past track record in settling
these claims. We will know this
through the latest available data, which is according to the IRDA's
Annual Report
2022. The first metric
we will check is the claim settlement
ratio, that is,
how many claims has this insurance company settled out of 100 claims, that
is, if 100 claims are filed,
how many claims has this insurance company
settled within 1 year? What will this data
tell us? It will tell us about the insurance
company's claim settlement efficiency and
intention. The higher the claim
settlement ratio, the better the company's
intentions are to approve your claim.
So, the claim settlement ratio of SBI General Insurance
Company in the case of health insurance is
94, that is,
94 claims out of 100 claims  94 claims have been
approved by Parni. Apart from this, the
second important metric is the Income
Claim Ratio. This ratio tells us
how much money the insurance company has collected as premium from its policy holders
and how much of that money it has returned to the claim center. That is,
how strict or lenient the insurance company is in the matter of paying claims,
we estimate this from the Income Claim Ratio only. So,
if we take the average of all the health insurance companies, then the Income
Claim Ratio
comes around 80. This
is less than that at 8. So, there is still scope for improvement in this,
but it can be called the average Income Claim Ratio.
That means the company is dispersing claims well,
but to
pay a higher amount for the number of claims, the
insurance company must also have money of its own.
We can estimate this through solvency ratio
or solvency.  The
IRDA guideline for
solvency ratio for all insurance companies
is 1.5 times, which means that if an
insurance company has a
liability of ₹1 to its policyholders through its policies, then
it should always have ₹1
so that it does not fall short of money for claims. According to
SBI General Insurance Company
's latest annual
report for 2023-24, its
solvency margin is 2.25 times, which is
much above the IRDA guidelines, which
means that this company has comfortable
money available to give to its policyholders.
That is why the credit rating
agencies that have rated SBI General Insurance Company have
given it a rating of Triple A and a stable outlook. This
means that
after checking Financial Express, it is time to understand its claim
process. We have taken the policy and the
insurance company is also processing and approving claims easily,
but what is its
claim process like?  What process do we have to go through
during any health insurance claim? As you know, there are
two types of claims.
Cashless claim is the one you should always prefer,
and its process is also quite easy.
You have to visit a network hospital and
file a claim there.
After submitting all the treatment and insured documents,
you will get approval there, and after that, you
can get treatment. This is a very easy process,
but where are these network hospitals
available? You will find 177,000 plus hospitals all over India.
SBI General
Insurance has a good network of
these cashless hospitals. You will have to check
their cashless hospitals by visiting their website. Keep in
mind that the
network hospitals of the TPAs ​​mentioned in your policy should be in your city.
Where will you check this?
I am giving you the link in the description of this video. There is
no need to go anywhere. Click on that link.
Enter the pin code of your city, and as soon as you
search, the cashless hospitals in your city will appear in
front of you.  The second type
of claim is a reimbursement claim. Suppose
we went to a network hospital and did
not receive cashless treatment approval from the
company, or we
took treatment at a non-network hospital, or
we want to claim pre- and post-hospitalization expenses.
How can we do that?
For this, you only have an offline method.
You cannot get the claim approved by scanning the online documents and sending them to the website.
You will have to send the physical documents
either through courier to the
head office address mentioned on their website.
Or, if
you have an SBI General branch
near you or in your city, you can also submit all the
claim-related
documents there, be it the claim form,
doctor's prescription,
invoice, lab reports, etc., after getting all these
documents signed and stamped, and
submit them to the nearest branch.
Health insurance companies that
adopt the offline reimbursement method are
mistake-proof.  Fake
claims can be made in it. Chances of mistakes
are less but it becomes a little inconvenient for the client and the policy holder.
Now friends, it is the turn to know the
very important contact details of SBI General Insurance Company.
If you
have their policy or are thinking of buying it
or you have any product
of this company, then you must have these contact
details because the
coverage in the insurance policy mostly covers us only
if there is any sudden loss.
If we do not have these details at
that time, then we can face a lot of
problems. So the first important
detail is the toll free number. The
toll free number of SBI General Insurance Company is
18210 3366. It also has another toll free number
18210 6366. If you want to send any of your matters
in writing to them, then you can also email
customercare@sbicard.com.
Apart from this, you will get many other self-help services.
I am giving you the link of this Quick Assist web page
in the description of this video.  If you
need self-help services related to any policy, then directly click on this link
and
you can directly apply for any services yourself.
And now finally comes the matter.
If we have any complaint with this insurance company, if we
want to file a complaint, our claim was
not heard, money was deducted from the claim amount,
some changes need to be made in the policy,
service is not being provided on time, then
you can also complain about it
in the Grievances Department. What is its step-by-step
process?
I am also giving you the link of the process of filing a grievance
in the description of this video.
Click on the link in front of Grievances
and definitely review the entire process once.
So that if tomorrow you have any complaint with this company,
any problem
in filing a claim or related to any other service, then
you should at least know what your
next step is. Now till here
friends, you have learned
all the important aspects of SBI General Insurance Company which
we should understand as policy holders, that is,
which
plans does the company offer?  What are the details of the
claim? What is the process of the
claim? Now after knowing this,
finally, what is my opinion about the conclusion of this video,
what is my opinion? That is,
what good things did I see in this company and what
shortcomings do I see? First of all, let's talk about
some good things. The first
plus point that I have seen is a good
claim settlement ratio, which is a
very good claim settlement ratio of 94, that is, the
number of claims that the company is settling for
its policy holders is quite
good and the incoming claim ratio of this company is
also not bad. The
incoming claim ratio of 72 can be counted
among the very good incoming claim ratios after a little improvement.
So this ratio is also fine, that is, the
overall claim intentions of the insurance company seem to be
fine. The
second plus point is its low
complaints, which is the industry average. The
number of complaints is at  10,000 claims equals
24 complaints. This means that for every 10,000 claims, 24
complaints are filed as an industry average
in health insurance. However, this
company's number of complaints per
year is only 13 complaints per 10,000 claims, which is
almost half the industry
average, which is a very positive point
for SBI General Insurance Company. The
final plus point comes from a strong parent. Having
SBI parentage is very good
for this company, both
in terms of financial strength and management, i.e., in the
way of working.
Apart from this, two private equity
investors are also involved in this company, who
track the profitability of the company
and maintain its innovative approach.
Now, friends, let's talk about some of the shortcomings
that I noticed in SBI General Insurance
Company. The first negative point is
that the availability of plans, the
portfolio of plans, is very
limited. If I
want to buy a personal health insurance policy for myself, then their plans under the
name Super Health Insurance and Health Hedge are very good.  These are the only two basic
plans available, as this company's
primary focus is on its group health
insurance products, which they
sell through SBI branches, whether they are
personal accidental policies or health
insurance policies. Therefore, having only two plans does
n't give me a sufficient choice in choosing a
personal health insurance plan
from this company. Although
you'll find five variants within the Super Health Insurance Plan, there's only one
option.
If there's a shortcoming
that doesn't meet my needs,
I have no other option. The
second negative point is regarding TPA claim
settlement. Health
insurance companies that have in-house claim
settlement, i.e., those companies that settle
claims directly, have a
slightly more efficient claim process.
Policies are convenient for older adults, take
less time, and require fewer hospital visits.
Adding a TPA to your health insurance policy
adds another member to the overall claim process,
which
increases the time required.  It increases inefficiency and
along with this it also increases the cost of the entire ecosystem
which directly impacts our
policy premium. The final
negative point that I see in SB General
Insurance Company is
regarding the services of the toll free number of this company.
I tried it myself and once I called,
no one received the call for 10 minutes. The waiting list kept saying that there is too
much congestion, hail is too much, your
call is very important for us, please wait.
After waiting for 10 minutes there was
no response and the call automatically
disconnected. When I
tried again, my call got connected after almost 16 minutes.
After 16 minutes I spoke to their
executive and then I talked to him as per my knowledge and
I felt that this is a very long
time. I told him that
we use health insurance in case of emergency, so at
that time we need some guidance,
some information, some
query, so in that time of emergency this
conversation should be very quick,
who will wait so much time, in any emergency
your IVR  The options certainly keep saying
that you are very important to us, your
call is very important to us, but
this will be known by how quickly you
connect with us. If the call connects after 10 to 20 minutes, then there is
no need to repeat this on the IVR to see
how convenient our call is for you. The
waiting time of this call itself tells us
how important our call is for you. So, the
insurance company should make some improvements in this service as well. So
friends,
you saw this report card video of the health insurance business of SBI General Insurance Company.
We have tried to include all the important aspects
and have
also told you our opinion about this company.
How has your experience been with SBI General Insurance Company, whether it has been good or
bad, you
can mention that too in the comments section. And please do let us know
how you liked the Report Card series by
commenting in the comments section.
If you have not seen the videos of other companies in the Report Card series
and want to know about them too, then you
can watch the entire series by clicking here. I am Harvinder
Singh. Now, tell us about it.  I will take your permission
in the next video, till then take
care of yourself, stay happy and healthy, Jai
Hind